<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- GRACE-lite Development Plan -->
<development-plan>
  <meta>
    <project-name>KrotVPN</project-name>
    <version>2.6.1</version>
    <updated>2026-03-27</updated>
    <current-phase>Manual internal client provisioning parity live-validated on fresh RU and DE infrastructure and released in v2.4.24</current-phase>
  </meta>

  <status-summary>
    <done>
      Backend, user frontend, admin frontend, bot and deploy surface already exist as an MVP.
      VPN topology has moved toward VPNNode/VPNRoute but routing policy is still mostly IP-based.
    </done>
    <in-progress>
      Synchronizing GRACE shared artifacts with the real codebase.
      Designing a policy-driven routing layer that can classify traffic by domain and IP.
      Designing a backend-driven manual provisioning path so operator-created configs match web-generated configs.
    </in-progress>
    <blocked-or-weak>
      Existing split-tunneling logic is too rigid for domain-level routing.
      Verification is still weaker than required for autonomous changes in routing-critical code.
    </blocked-or-weak>
  </status-summary>

  <active-workstreams>
    <WS-001 priority="critical" status="active">
      <name>AI Handoff and Documentation Accuracy</name>
      <goal>Keep GRACE artifacts aligned with the implemented system and planned migration path.</goal>
    </WS-001>
    <WS-002 priority="critical" status="active">
      <name>Security and Deployment Hardening</name>
      <goal>Reduce operational risk in secrets handling, admin access and deployment defaults.</goal>
    </WS-002>
    <WS-003 priority="critical" status="active">
      <name>VPN Topology and Provisioning Stability</name>
      <goal>Finish stabilizing VPNNode/VPNRoute-based provisioning and analytics invariants.</goal>
    </WS-003>
    <WS-004 priority="high" status="active">
      <name>Flexible Routing Policy Migration</name>
      <goal>
        Introduce a routing decision engine that supports exact-domain, wildcard-domain, DNS-bound IP
        and CIDR-based classification without breaking the current RU-vs-non-RU baseline.
      </goal>
    </WS-004>
    <WS-005 priority="high" status="planned">
      <name>Verification and Testability</name>
      <goal>Raise routing, VPN and admin verification to a level safe for autonomous execution.</goal>
    </WS-005>
    <WS-006 priority="critical" status="planned">
      <name>Manual Internal Client Provisioning</name>
      <goal>Replace raw host-only client config generation with a backend-driven internal-access flow that produces the same working configs as the web path.</goal>
    </WS-006>
  </active-workstreams>

  <module-catalog>
    <M-001 name="backend-core" type="UTILITY" priority="critical" verification-ref="V-M-001">
      <purpose>Configuration, security, DB lifecycle and bootstrap primitives.</purpose>
      <target-paths>backend/app/core</target-paths>
      <depends>none</depends>
    </M-001>
    <M-002 name="users" type="CORE_LOGIC" priority="critical" verification-ref="V-M-002">
      <purpose>User auth, profile and Telegram-linked identity flows.</purpose>
      <target-paths>backend/app/users</target-paths>
      <depends>M-001</depends>
    </M-002>
    <M-003 name="vpn" type="CORE_LOGIC" priority="critical" verification-ref="V-M-003">
      <purpose>VPN provisioning, config generation and topology-aware client assignment.</purpose>
      <target-paths>backend/app/vpn</target-paths>
      <depends>M-001 M-002 M-007</depends>
    </M-003>
    <M-004 name="billing" type="CORE_LOGIC" priority="critical" verification-ref="V-M-004">
      <purpose>Plans, subscriptions, payments and webhook processing.</purpose>
      <target-paths>backend/app/billing</target-paths>
      <depends>M-001</depends>
    </M-004>
    <M-005 name="referrals" type="CORE_LOGIC" priority="high" verification-ref="V-M-005">
      <purpose>Referral codes, links and bonus accounting.</purpose>
      <target-paths>backend/app/referrals</target-paths>
      <depends>M-001</depends>
    </M-005>
    <M-006 name="admin-api" type="ENTRY_POINT" priority="high" verification-ref="V-M-006">
      <purpose>Privileged analytics and operational control endpoints.</purpose>
      <target-paths>backend/app/admin</target-paths>
      <depends>M-001 M-002 M-003 M-004 M-005 M-007</depends>
    </M-006>
    <M-007 name="routing" type="INTEGRATION" priority="critical" verification-ref="V-M-007">
      <purpose>Host-level split-tunneling, ipset/iptables coordination and routing health inspection.</purpose>
      <target-paths>backend/app/routing</target-paths>
      <depends>M-001</depends>
    </M-007>
    <M-008 name="tasks" type="UTILITY" priority="medium" verification-ref="V-M-008">
      <purpose>Background scheduling and recurring maintenance jobs.</purpose>
      <target-paths>backend/app/tasks</target-paths>
      <depends>M-001</depends>
    </M-008>
    <M-009 name="frontend-user" type="UI_COMPONENT" priority="high" verification-ref="V-M-009">
      <purpose>Main user UI for auth, config delivery, subscription and referrals.</purpose>
      <target-paths>frontend</target-paths>
      <depends>M-002 M-003 M-004 M-005</depends>
    </M-009>
    <M-010 name="frontend-admin" type="UI_COMPONENT" priority="high" verification-ref="V-M-010">
      <purpose>Admin UI for analytics, plans, users, servers and routing surfaces.</purpose>
      <target-paths>frontend-admin</target-paths>
      <depends>M-006</depends>
    </M-010>
    <M-011 name="telegram-bot" type="ENTRY_POINT" priority="medium" verification-ref="V-M-011">
      <purpose>Telegram bot orchestration over backend HTTP APIs.</purpose>
      <target-paths>telegram-bot</target-paths>
      <depends>M-002 M-003 M-004</depends>
    </M-011>
    <M-012 name="deploy-surface" type="ENTRY_POINT" priority="critical" verification-ref="V-M-012">
      <purpose>Install, deploy, nginx and compose surfaces that shape production behavior.</purpose>
      <target-paths>deploy install.sh nginx docker-compose.yml</target-paths>
      <depends>M-003 M-007</depends>
    </M-012>
    <M-013 name="route-policy-resolver" type="CORE_LOGIC" priority="critical" verification-ref="V-M-013">
      <purpose>
        Decide routing target using explicit domain rules, DNS-bound addresses, explicit CIDR rules and fallback policy.
      </purpose>
      <target-paths>backend/app/routing/policy.py</target-paths>
      <depends>M-001 M-007</depends>
    </M-013>
    <M-014 name="domain-rule-store" type="DATA_LAYER" priority="critical" verification-ref="V-M-014">
      <purpose>Persist exact, wildcard and priority-ordered routing rules for domains and CIDRs.</purpose>
      <target-paths>backend/app/routing/domain_rules.py backend/app/routing/models.py</target-paths>
      <depends>M-001</depends>
    </M-014>
    <M-015 name="dns-observer" type="INTEGRATION" priority="high" verification-ref="V-M-015">
      <purpose>Track domain-to-IP bindings from DNS resolution and maintain TTL-aware policy cache updates.</purpose>
      <target-paths>backend/app/routing/dns_resolver.py</target-paths>
      <depends>M-001 M-013 M-014</depends>
    </M-015>
    <M-016 name="route-decision-api" type="ENTRY_POINT" priority="high" verification-ref="V-M-016">
      <purpose>Expose admin controls and inspection endpoints for routing policy rules and effective decisions.</purpose>
      <target-paths>backend/app/routing/router.py backend/app/admin/router.py frontend-admin</target-paths>
      <depends>M-006 M-007 M-013 M-014 M-015</depends>
    </M-016>
    <M-017 name="route-sync-runtime" type="INTEGRATION" priority="critical" verification-ref="V-M-017">
      <purpose>Translate resolved policy decisions into host-level routing sets and incremental refresh actions.</purpose>
      <target-paths>backend/app/routing/manager.py</target-paths>
      <depends>M-007 M-013 M-014 M-015</depends>
    </M-017>
    <M-018 name="manual-access-policy" type="CORE_LOGIC" priority="critical" verification-ref="V-M-018">
      <purpose>Grant and reuse internal non-billable access for operator-managed users without bypassing the main subscription and provisioning model.</purpose>
      <target-paths>backend/app/users/service.py backend/app/billing/service.py backend/app/billing/models.py</target-paths>
      <depends>M-001 M-002 M-003 M-004</depends>
    </M-018>
    <M-019 name="manual-client-cli" type="ENTRY_POINT" priority="critical" verification-ref="V-M-019">
      <purpose>Create or reuse an internal user, ensure complimentary access, provision a VPN client, and export a working config through backend CLI.</purpose>
      <target-paths>backend/app/cli.py deploy/create-client.sh</target-paths>
      <depends>M-001 M-002 M-003 M-004 M-012 M-018</depends>
    </M-019>
  </module-catalog>

  <data-flows>
    <DF-001>
      <name>Domain-first routing decision</name>
      <path>M-016 -> M-013 -> M-014 -> M-017</path>
      <summary>
        Admin-defined domain policy is evaluated first. Exact and wildcard domain rules override generic RU IP heuristics.
      </summary>
    </DF-001>
    <DF-002>
      <name>DNS binding to runtime route set</name>
      <path>M-015 -> M-013 -> M-017</path>
      <summary>
        DNS-derived IPs for a matched domain are cached and synchronized into the runtime route set with TTL awareness.
      </summary>
    </DF-002>
    <DF-003>
      <name>Fallback CIDR classification</name>
      <path>M-013 -> M-014 -> M-017</path>
      <summary>
        If no domain policy applies, explicit CIDR rules and the RU baseline determine whether traffic stays local or exits via DE.
      </summary>
    </DF-003>
    <DF-004>
      <name>Provisioning and config consistency</name>
      <path>M-003 -> M-013 -> M-017</path>
      <summary>
        VPN provisioning and routing runtime share the same decision policy so client expectations match traffic behavior.
      </summary>
    </DF-004>
    <DF-005>
      <name>Admin observability of policy decisions</name>
      <path>M-006 -> M-016 -> M-013</path>
      <summary>
        Operators can inspect why a domain or IP was routed to RU, DE, DIRECT or DEFAULT.
      </summary>
    </DF-005>
    <DF-006>
      <name>Manual internal client provisioning</name>
      <path>M-019 -> M-002 -> M-018 -> M-003</path>
      <summary>
        Operator-run client creation resolves or creates an internal user, grants non-billable access, provisions a VPN client and returns the same config shape as the web flow.
      </summary>
    </DF-006>
    <DF-007>
      <name>Config parity between web and CLI paths</name>
      <path>M-002 -> M-004 -> M-003 and M-019 -> M-018 -> M-003</path>
      <summary>
        Web registration and operator CLI issuance must converge on the same VPNService-based topology selection and config rendering path.
      </summary>
    </DF-007>
    <DF-008>
      <name>Manual client idempotency and reprovision safety</name>
      <path>M-019 -> M-018 -> M-003</path>
      <summary>
        Re-running manual client issuance for the same identity should reuse or explicitly reprovision state instead of creating silent duplicate active clients.
      </summary>
    </DF-008>
  </data-flows>

  <implementation-order>
    <Phase-1 status="done">
      <name>Policy model and safe compatibility layer</name>
      <step-1>Create M-014 rule entities and schemas for exact-domain, wildcard-domain and CIDR rules.</step-1>
      <step-2>Create M-013 resolver with deterministic precedence: domain exact, domain wildcard, DNS-bound IP, explicit CIDR, RU baseline, default.</step-2>
      <step-3>Keep current RU-vs-non-RU behavior as fallback so rollout remains backward compatible.</step-3>
    </Phase-1>
    <Phase-2 status="done">
      <name>Runtime synchronization and DNS binding</name>
      <step-1>Extend M-017 runtime sync so policy changes become incremental host-level updates instead of full resets where possible.</step-1>
      <step-2>Add M-015 DNS observer and bounded cache with TTL-driven expiry and refresh.</step-2>
      <step-3>Introduce decision logging anchors for every policy branch.</step-3>
    </Phase-2>
    <Phase-3 status="done">
      <name>Admin control plane and operator visibility</name>
      <step-1>Extend M-016 with CRUD for domain rules and read-only decision inspection endpoints.</step-1>
      <step-2>Expose policy and resolution state in the admin frontend without changing the user-facing product flow yet.</step-2>
      <step-3>Add migration-safe analytics so legacy VPNServer-based views do not silently misrepresent routing state.</step-3>
    </Phase-3>
    <Phase-4 status="done">
      <name>Hardening and rollout gates</name>
      <step-1>Run routing-focused verification on exact-domain, wildcard-domain, TTL expiry and fallback branches.</step-1>
      <step-2>Gate production rollout on host-level safety review for ipset or nftables updates.</step-2>
      <step-3>Only after evidence is stable, make domain-aware policy the preferred routing control surface.</step-3>
    </Phase-4>
    <Phase-5 status="done">
      <name>Manual internal access and CLI provisioning parity</name>
      <step-1>Add an internal non-billable access model that remains visible in normal user, subscription and VPN state instead of bypassing billing and provisioning.</step-1>
      <step-2>Add backend CLI orchestration that creates or resolves the internal user, ensures access, provisions the client and exports config through VPNService.</step-2>
      <step-3>Convert deploy/create-client.sh into a thin wrapper over the backend CLI so manual configs no longer use raw host-only generation.</step-3>
      <step-4>Verify parity between manually issued configs and web-issued configs, including idempotency and restart-safe peer persistence.</step-4>
    </Phase-5>
  </implementation-order>

  <observability-notes>
    <item>Every route decision must include a stable reason code: domain_exact, domain_wildcard, dns_bound_ip, cidr_rule, ru_baseline, default.</item>
    <item>DNS binding refresh must emit stable logs for add, refresh, expire and conflict branches.</item>
    <item>Runtime sync must expose whether a rule was applied incrementally, skipped, or required a full refresh.</item>
    <item>Manual client issuance must emit stable markers for request, identity resolution, complimentary access grant, provisioning outcome and config export.</item>
  </observability-notes>

  <mental-walkthroughs>
    <scenario id="MW-001">
      <name>Known Russian domain</name>
      <summary>
        Client requests a domain matched by an exact or wildcard RU rule. Resolver returns RU without depending on the current resolved IP.
      </summary>
    </scenario>
    <scenario id="MW-002">
      <name>Known foreign domain behind changing CDN IPs</name>
      <summary>
        Domain rule sends traffic to DE. DNS observer keeps the changing IP set aligned so CDN drift does not collapse policy correctness.
      </summary>
    </scenario>
    <scenario id="MW-003">
      <name>Unknown domain with no explicit rule</name>
      <summary>
        Resolver falls back to explicit CIDR policy and finally the existing RU baseline, preserving current behavior until policy coverage grows.
      </summary>
    </scenario>
    <scenario id="MW-004">
      <name>Operator creates internal client for family use</name>
      <summary>
        Admin runs the manual client command, backend resolves or creates an internal identity, grants non-billable access, provisions a VPN client and returns a config that matches the normal user flow.
      </summary>
    </scenario>
    <scenario id="MW-005">
      <name>Repeated manual issue for the same client name</name>
      <summary>
        CLI resolves the same internal identity and reuses or explicitly reprovisions the existing client rather than creating hidden duplicate state with a different peer or IP.
      </summary>
    </scenario>
  </mental-walkthroughs>

  <risks>
    <item>Domain-aware routing is incomplete if DNS bindings are not captured before traffic reaches only-IP enforcement points.</item>
    <item>CDN and shared-IP domains can cause false sharing unless rule priority and conflict handling are explicit.</item>
    <item>Host-level rule churn can degrade stability if runtime sync is not incremental and bounded.</item>
    <item>Admin analytics can drift from real routing behavior if legacy VPNServer assumptions remain unadjusted.</item>
    <item>Manual client issuance will remain unreliable if deploy/create-client.sh keeps generating peers and configs outside backend topology and subscription state.</item>
    <item>Internal non-billable access can pollute billing analytics unless complimentary access is explicitly marked and reported.</item>
    <item>Unsafe reprovision rules could create duplicate active clients or mismatched peer state for the same internal identity.</item>
  </risks>
</development-plan>
