<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- GRACE-lite Verification Plan -->
<verification-plan>
  <meta>
    <project-name>KrotVPN</project-name>
    <version>2.7.0</version>
    <updated>2026-03-27</updated>
  </meta>

  <verification-philosophy>
    <principle>Routing decisions must be explainable, deterministic and safe to replay from logs.</principle>
    <principle>Domain-aware routing is not verified unless domain rules, DNS binding and host-level runtime sync are checked together.</principle>
    <principle>If host tools or dependencies are unavailable, the report must state the exact blocked command and missing prerequisite.</principle>
    <principle>Manual operator-issued VPN configs are not verified unless they are generated through the same backend provisioning and config-rendering path as the working web flow.</principle>
    <principle>Per-plan device limits are not trusted unless device creation, revoke and rotate operations are verified against explicit active-device counts.</principle>
    <principle>Anti-sharing enforcement must separate deterministic device-limit checks from probabilistic handshake anomaly signals and should default to detect-first evidence before auto-blocking.</principle>
  </verification-philosophy>

  <critical-flows>
    <CF-001>register -> trial subscription -> vpn config delivery -> domain-aware route resolution</CF-001>
    <CF-002>login -> protected API access -> known RU domain stays local or RU-routed by policy</CF-002>
    <CF-003>foreign domain with changing CDN IPs -> DNS rebinding -> DE policy remains effective</CF-003>
    <CF-004>admin updates routing rule -> runtime sync applies changes without breaking unrelated routes</CF-004>
    <CF-005>unknown domain -> CIDR fallback -> RU baseline or default path remains backward compatible</CF-005>
    <CF-006>manual internal client command -> complimentary access grant -> vpn client provisioning -> working config export</CF-006>
    <CF-007>repeat manual internal client command -> same identity reuse or explicit reprovision -> no silent duplicate active client</CF-007>
    <CF-008>user with active subscription -> create device -> plan device limit enforced before peer provisioning</CF-008>
    <CF-009>user revokes one device -> slot is freed -> user creates a new device -> new peer works and old peer stops</CF-009>
    <CF-010>user rotates a compromised device config -> same logical device remains -> old peer stops -> new peer works</CF-010>
    <CF-011>same peer reused from suspiciously different endpoints -> anomaly event recorded -> admin can block only that device</CF-011>
    <CF-012>blocked device peer stays unusable while unrelated devices under the same user remain functional</CF-012>
  </critical-flows>

  <verification-matrix>
    <scenario id="VM-001" module="V-M-013" evidence="deterministic">
      <success>Exact-domain rule wins over wildcard, CIDR and baseline.</success>
      <failure>Resolver returns weaker precedence branch when exact rule exists.</failure>
      <required-trace>ROUTE_DECISION_DOMAIN_EXACT</required-trace>
    </scenario>
    <scenario id="VM-002" module="V-M-013" evidence="deterministic">
      <success>Wildcard-domain rule wins when exact rule is absent.</success>
      <failure>Resolver skips wildcard and falls into CIDR or baseline unexpectedly.</failure>
      <required-trace>ROUTE_DECISION_DOMAIN_WILDCARD</required-trace>
    </scenario>
    <scenario id="VM-003" module="V-M-015" evidence="trace-plus-state">
      <success>DNS binding refresh updates active IP set before stale TTL entries leak indefinitely.</success>
      <failure>Expired binding remains active or new binding is not propagated.</failure>
      <required-trace>DNS_BINDING_UPDATED DNS_BINDING_EXPIRED</required-trace>
    </scenario>
    <scenario id="VM-004" module="V-M-017" evidence="trace-plus-state">
      <success>Runtime sync applies only affected route-set changes for a single rule mutation.</success>
      <failure>Unrelated route sets are flushed or stale entries remain.</failure>
      <required-trace>RUNTIME_ROUTESET_INCREMENTAL</required-trace>
    </scenario>
    <scenario id="VM-005" module="V-M-016" evidence="deterministic-plus-auth">
      <success>Admin can inspect policy state and decision reasons, non-admin cannot mutate policy.</success>
      <failure>Missing auth enforcement or missing reason field in response.</failure>
      <required-trace>ROUTE_DECISION_DOMAIN_EXACT plus response-shape and auth assertions in API tests</required-trace>
    </scenario>
    <scenario id="VM-006" module="V-M-003" evidence="integration">
      <success>VPN provisioning still produces config consistent with selected topology and routing policy expectations.</success>
      <failure>Route-aware provisioning diverges from effective runtime policy.</failure>
      <required-trace>VPN_PROVISION_ROUTE_SELECTED VPN_CONFIG_RENDERED</required-trace>
    </scenario>
    <scenario id="VM-007" module="V-M-018" evidence="state-plus-policy">
      <success>Manual internal access grant creates or reuses a clearly marked non-billable access record without invoking payment-provider logic.</success>
      <failure>Internal access is missing, duplicated, or silently mixed with normal paid subscription state.</failure>
      <required-trace>VPN_INTERNAL_USER_RESOLVED VPN_INTERNAL_ACCESS_GRANTED</required-trace>
    </scenario>
    <scenario id="VM-008" module="V-M-019" evidence="integration">
      <success>Operator CLI issues a working config through backend provisioning and config rendering, and repeated issuance stays idempotent unless reprovision is explicit.</success>
      <failure>CLI falls back to raw host-only config generation, or duplicate active client state is created for the same internal identity.</failure>
      <required-trace>VPN_MANUAL_CLIENT_REQUESTED VPN_MANUAL_CLIENT_PROVISIONED VPN_CONFIG_RENDERED</required-trace>
    </scenario>
    <scenario id="VM-009" module="V-M-021" evidence="deterministic-plus-state">
      <success>Device creation is rejected when active device count has reached the effective plan limit.</success>
      <failure>A new peer is provisioned despite the plan limit, or the system counts revoked or blocked devices incorrectly.</failure>
      <required-trace>VPN_DEVICE_CREATE_REQUESTED VPN_DEVICE_LIMIT_REJECTED</required-trace>
    </scenario>
    <scenario id="VM-010" module="V-M-022" evidence="integration">
      <success>Revoking a device disables only that device peer and allows a new device to be created in the freed slot.</success>
      <failure>Old peer remains active, slot is not freed, or another unrelated device is affected.</failure>
      <required-trace>VPN_DEVICE_REVOKED VPN_DEVICE_CREATED</required-trace>
    </scenario>
    <scenario id="VM-011" module="V-M-022" evidence="integration">
      <success>Rotating a config keeps the same logical device but replaces its peer and invalidates the old config.</success>
      <failure>Rotate creates a hidden second device or leaves the old peer usable.</failure>
      <required-trace>VPN_DEVICE_CONFIG_ROTATED VPN_PEER_APPLIED</required-trace>
    </scenario>
    <scenario id="VM-012" module="V-M-023" evidence="trace-plus-state">
      <success>Suspicious endpoint churn or near-concurrent peer reuse produces a stable anomaly event and raises device suspicion without immediately corrupting unrelated device state.</success>
      <failure>Suspicious reuse leaves no structured evidence, or the wrong device is blamed.</failure>
      <required-trace>VPN_HANDSHAKE_OBSERVED VPN_HANDSHAKE_ENDPOINT_CHANGED VPN_HANDSHAKE_CONCURRENCY_SUSPECTED</required-trace>
    </scenario>
    <scenario id="VM-013" module="V-M-024" evidence="integration-plus-auth">
      <success>Admin can block or unblock a specific device peer and non-admin users cannot invoke the same enforcement surface.</success>
      <failure>Enforcement bypasses auth or disables the whole user account instead of the targeted device.</failure>
      <required-trace>VPN_DEVICE_BLOCKED VPN_DEVICE_UNBLOCKED</required-trace>
    </scenario>
    <scenario id="VM-014" module="V-M-025" evidence="deterministic">
      <success>Every device lifecycle or anomaly transition produces an audit record with device_id, user_id and event type.</success>
      <failure>Security-relevant actions occur without a durable audit trail.</failure>
      <required-trace>VPN_DEVICE_AUDIT_RECORDED</required-trace>
    </scenario>
  </verification-matrix>

  <module-verification>
    <V-M-001 module="backend-core">
      <checks>Backend config and DB initialization remain runnable; auth and crypto helpers still load.</checks>
      <evidence>backend startup or targeted import/test reasoning</evidence>
    </V-M-001>
    <V-M-002 module="users">
      <checks>Identity creation stays deterministic for both normal and internal users, and manual internal-user resolution cannot create duplicate user rows for the same logical client.</checks>
      <tests>backend/tests/test_telegram_auth.py backend/tests/test_manual_access_policy.py backend/tests/test_manual_client_cli.py</tests>
      <anchors>VPN_INTERNAL_USER_RESOLVED</anchors>
    </V-M-002>
    <V-M-003 module="vpn">
      <checks>Provisioning and config generation remain compatible with route-aware topology, including configs exported for operator-managed internal clients.</checks>
      <tests>backend/tests/test_vpn_service.py backend/tests/test_vpn_router_compat.py backend/tests/test_manual_client_cli.py</tests>
      <anchors>VPN_PROVISION_ROUTE_SELECTED VPN_CONFIG_RENDERED VPN_PEER_APPLIED</anchors>
    </V-M-003>
    <V-M-004 module="billing">
      <checks>Payment and webhook flows remain isolated from routing migration, and complimentary internal access can be granted without entering payment-provider logic.</checks>
      <tests>backend/tests/test_billing_security.py backend/tests/test_manual_access_policy.py</tests>
      <anchors>BILLING_WEBHOOK_ACCEPTED BILLING_SUBSCRIPTION_UPDATED VPN_INTERNAL_ACCESS_GRANTED</anchors>
    </V-M-004>
    <V-M-005 module="referrals">
      <checks>Referral logic remains excluded from manual internal client issuance unless explicitly requested by future policy.</checks>
      <tests>static review plus future targeted referral-policy tests if manual issuance ever intersects referral creation</tests>
      <anchors>none-required-for-current-scope</anchors>
    </V-M-005>
    <V-M-006 module="admin-api">
      <checks>Admin routing inspection and analytics endpoints enforce admin auth and reflect current policy state.</checks>
      <tests>backend/tests/test_route_decision_api.py backend/tests/test_admin_stats.py</tests>
      <anchors>none-required-for-current-scope; current evidence is admin auth plus response-shape verification in route and stats API tests</anchors>
    </V-M-006>
    <V-M-007 module="routing">
      <checks>Current RU ipset update, custom route sync and tunnel inspection remain safe under host-level assumptions.</checks>
      <tests>backend/tests/test_routing_policy_compat.py plus static review and targeted runtime tests when host tools are available</tests>
      <anchors>RUNTIME_ROUTESET_INCREMENTAL RUNTIME_ROUTESET_FULL_REFRESH</anchors>
    </V-M-007>
    <V-M-008 module="tasks">
      <checks>Background jobs do not auto-assign complimentary internal access or mutate manually managed clients unexpectedly.</checks>
      <tests>static review until a task is introduced for internal-access cleanup or reporting</tests>
      <anchors>none-required-for-current-scope</anchors>
    </V-M-008>
    <V-M-009 module="frontend-user">
      <checks>User frontend still builds and has no contract mismatch with auth, config and subscription APIs.</checks>
      <commands>cd frontend &amp;&amp; npm run build</commands>
    </V-M-009>
    <V-M-010 module="frontend-admin">
      <checks>Admin frontend builds and reflects new route policy surfaces without auth regression.</checks>
      <commands>cd frontend-admin &amp;&amp; npm run build</commands>
    </V-M-010>
    <V-M-011 module="telegram-bot">
      <checks>Telegram bot remains on the normal user flow and does not silently consume internal-only manual provisioning paths.</checks>
      <tests>backend/tests/test_telegram_auth.py plus static review of telegram-bot/bot.py call surfaces</tests>
      <anchors>none-required-for-current-scope</anchors>
    </V-M-011>
    <V-M-012 module="deploy-surface">
      <checks>Deploy and nginx changes do not introduce weak defaults or unsafe routing assumptions, deploy/create-client.sh becomes a thin wrapper over backend CLI instead of generating raw host-only configs, and fresh RU deploys install a host-level awg0 sync watcher so backend-written peers become active on the live interface.</checks>
      <commands>bash -n deploy/deploy-ru-server.sh &amp;&amp; bash -n deploy/deploy-on-server.sh &amp;&amp; bash -n deploy/deploy-all.sh &amp;&amp; bash -n deploy/create-client.sh &amp;&amp; bash -n install.sh</commands>
      <evidence>static review of secrets, ports, mounts, backend CLI invocation, host tool expectations and awg0 watcher install path; live RU evidence should include HTTPS reachability, backend health, live tunnel handshake and peer appearance in awg show after both manual and web provisioning</evidence>
    </V-M-012>
    <V-M-013 module="route-policy-resolver">
      <checks>
        Exact-domain rules override wildcard rules, wildcard rules override CIDR, CIDR overrides RU baseline,
        and fallback remains deterministic when no rule matches.
      </checks>
      <tests>backend/tests/test_route_policy_resolver.py</tests>
      <anchors>
        ROUTE_DECISION_DOMAIN_EXACT ROUTE_DECISION_DOMAIN_WILDCARD ROUTE_DECISION_DNS_BOUND_IP
        ROUTE_DECISION_CIDR ROUTE_DECISION_RU_BASELINE ROUTE_DECISION_FALLBACK
      </anchors>
    </V-M-013>
    <V-M-014 module="domain-rule-store">
      <checks>Rule persistence preserves priority, activation state, domain normalization and duplicate handling.</checks>
      <tests>backend/tests/test_domain_rule_store.py</tests>
      <anchors>none-required-for-current-scope; current evidence is persistence, normalization and duplicate-handling behavior in store tests</anchors>
    </V-M-014>
    <V-M-015 module="dns-observer">
      <checks>DNS bindings are refreshed by TTL, expired safely and conflict resolution is explicit.</checks>
      <tests>backend/tests/test_dns_observer.py</tests>
      <anchors>DNS_BINDING_UPDATED DNS_BINDING_EXPIRED DNS_BINDING_CONFLICT</anchors>
    </V-M-015>
    <V-M-016 module="route-decision-api">
      <checks>Admin CRUD and inspection endpoints expose policy state safely and return decision reasons.</checks>
      <tests>backend/tests/test_route_decision_api.py</tests>
      <anchors>ROUTE_DECISION_DOMAIN_EXACT; current API evidence also relies on response-shape assertions for list, mutation and explain endpoints</anchors>
    </V-M-016>
    <V-M-017 module="route-sync-runtime">
      <checks>Runtime sync applies incremental updates correctly, removes stale bindings and avoids rule leakage between RU and DE sets.</checks>
      <tests>backend/tests/test_route_sync_runtime.py</tests>
      <anchors>RUNTIME_ROUTESET_INCREMENTAL RUNTIME_ROUTESET_FULL_REFRESH</anchors>
    </V-M-017>
    <V-M-018 module="manual-access-policy">
      <checks>Complimentary internal access is created or reused deterministically, remains visible in normal subscription state and does not invoke payment-provider side effects.</checks>
      <tests>backend/tests/test_manual_access_policy.py</tests>
      <anchors>VPN_INTERNAL_USER_RESOLVED VPN_INTERNAL_ACCESS_GRANTED</anchors>
    </V-M-018>
    <V-M-019 module="manual-client-cli">
      <checks>Manual CLI issuance resolves the internal identity, provisions through VPNService, exports a working config and stays idempotent unless reprovision is explicitly requested.</checks>
      <tests>backend/tests/test_manual_client_cli.py</tests>
      <anchors>VPN_MANUAL_CLIENT_REQUESTED VPN_MANUAL_CLIENT_PROVISIONED VPN_CONFIG_RENDERED VPN_MANUAL_CLIENT_OUTPUT_WRITTEN</anchors>
    </V-M-019>
    <V-M-020 module="device-registry">
      <checks>Device records preserve active, revoked, blocked and replaced lifecycle state; migrated legacy clients become deterministic primary devices without losing peer linkage.</checks>
      <tests>backend/tests/test_device_registry.py backend/tests/test_device_migration.py</tests>
      <anchors>VPN_DEVICE_CREATED VPN_DEVICE_AUDIT_RECORDED</anchors>
    </V-M-020>
    <V-M-021 module="device-access-policy">
      <checks>Effective plan device limits are enforced before provisioning, revoked devices free slots, blocked devices do not silently bypass policy, and rotate preserves logical device identity.</checks>
      <tests>backend/tests/test_device_access_policy.py</tests>
      <anchors>VPN_DEVICE_CREATE_REQUESTED VPN_DEVICE_LIMIT_REJECTED VPN_DEVICE_REVOKED VPN_DEVICE_CONFIG_ROTATED VPN_DEVICE_BLOCKED</anchors>
    </V-M-021>
    <V-M-022 module="device-provisioning-api">
      <checks>User-facing device APIs expose only the caller’s devices, allow deterministic create or revoke or rotate flows, and keep one peer per logical device.</checks>
      <tests>backend/tests/test_device_api.py backend/tests/test_vpn_router_compat.py</tests>
      <anchors>VPN_DEVICE_CREATED VPN_DEVICE_REVOKED VPN_DEVICE_CONFIG_ROTATED VPN_CONFIG_RENDERED</anchors>
    </V-M-022>
    <V-M-023 module="handshake-anomaly-detector">
      <checks>Handshake observation updates device last-seen state, flags suspicious endpoint churn or near-concurrent reuse, and does not leak secrets or raw private peer material into logs.</checks>
      <tests>backend/tests/test_handshake_anomaly_detector.py</tests>
      <anchors>VPN_HANDSHAKE_OBSERVED VPN_HANDSHAKE_ENDPOINT_CHANGED VPN_HANDSHAKE_CONCURRENCY_SUSPECTED VPN_DEVICE_SUSPICION_ESCALATED</anchors>
    </V-M-023>
    <V-M-024 module="device-admin-control">
      <checks>Admin endpoints can list devices, view anomaly state and block or unblock or revoke a specific device peer while preserving user-level auth boundaries.</checks>
      <tests>backend/tests/test_admin_device_control.py</tests>
      <anchors>VPN_DEVICE_BLOCKED VPN_DEVICE_UNBLOCKED VPN_DEVICE_REVOKED</anchors>
    </V-M-024>
    <V-M-025 module="device-audit-log">
      <checks>Every device lifecycle and anomaly escalation writes an audit entry with stable event types and enough context for later investigation.</checks>
      <tests>backend/tests/test_device_audit_log.py</tests>
      <anchors>VPN_DEVICE_AUDIT_RECORDED</anchors>
    </V-M-025>
  </module-verification>

  <change-matrix>
    <routing-policy-change>
      <required>Run or design targeted tests for V-M-013 through V-M-017.</required>
      <required>Review affected critical flow from CF-003 to CF-005.</required>
      <required>Confirm stable decision reason logs remain present.</required>
    </routing-policy-change>
    <vpn-or-routing-runtime-change>
      <required>High-scrutiny static review of host-level tools, assumptions and rollback path.</required>
      <required>Explain exactly which host-bound command could or could not be executed.</required>
    </vpn-or-routing-runtime-change>
    <admin-surface-change>
      <required>Verify admin auth, endpoint behavior and admin frontend compatibility.</required>
    </admin-surface-change>
    <manual-client-provisioning-change>
      <required>Verify CF-006 and CF-007 with backend CLI plus deploy/create-client.sh wrapper coverage.</required>
      <required>Confirm operator-created configs are rendered by VPNService rather than raw shell-generated templates.</required>
      <required>Confirm complimentary access remains distinguishable from paid subscriptions in state and reporting.</required>
      <required>Confirm host-level awg0 peer activation happens automatically after backend writes peer state, both for manual issuance and for web registration paths.</required>
    </manual-client-provisioning-change>
    <device-access-change>
      <required>Verify CF-008 through CF-012 with deterministic device counts before enabling autonomous execution on device-aware provisioning.</required>
      <required>Confirm device-limit checks run before peer creation and before address allocation.</required>
      <required>Confirm revoke, rotate and block flows leave an audit record and do not accidentally affect unrelated devices for the same user.</required>
      <required>Keep anomaly detection in detect-first mode until phase-level evidence shows false positives are bounded.</required>
    </device-access-change>
  </change-matrix>

  <telemetry-requirements>
    <format>
      Important routing logs should use stable machine-readable markers in the form
      [Routing][resolver][MARKER] or equivalent structured fields.
    </format>
    <manual-provisioning-format>
      Manual provisioning logs should use stable markers in the form
      [VPN][manual][MARKER] or [Billing][internal][MARKER].
    </manual-provisioning-format>
    <device-format>
      Device and anti-sharing logs should use stable markers in the form
      [VPN][device][MARKER] or [VPN][handshake][MARKER].
    </device-format>
    <redaction>
      Do not log secrets, private keys, raw tokens, payment credentials or full sensitive payloads.
    </redaction>
    <required-fields>
      decision_reason rule_id domain normalized_domain resolved_ip route_target source ttl_seconds sync_mode
    </required-fields>
    <manual-required-fields>
      internal_identity user_id access_mode complimentary subscription_id client_id route_id entry_node_id output_path reprovision
    </manual-required-fields>
    <device-required-fields>
      user_id device_id device_name device_status config_version peer_public_key last_endpoint suspicion_score event_type enforcement_action plan_id device_limit
    </device-required-fields>
    <ordering>
      For trace assertions, event order matters more than prose wording. Prefer stable markers and fields over free text.
    </ordering>
  </telemetry-requirements>

  <verification-levels>
    <module-level>
      Resolver precedence tests, domain normalization tests, admin auth checks, internal-access policy tests, CLI parity tests, device-limit policy tests and narrow runtime sync tests.
    </module-level>
    <wave-level>
      Merged checks across routing, vpn and admin surfaces for domain policy mutation, device-bound provisioning and admin enforcement.
    </wave-level>
    <phase-level>
      Full routing migration confidence gate plus device-limit and anti-sharing confidence gate including rollback reasoning, host-tool assumptions, deploy impact review, manual-client provisioning parity review and staged enforcement review.
    </phase-level>
  </verification-levels>

  <phase-gates>
    <Phase-1-Gate>
      <required>Resolver precedence tests defined and passing or explicitly blocked with reason.</required>
      <required>Backward-compatible fallback to current RU baseline preserved.</required>
    </Phase-1-Gate>
    <Phase-2-Gate>
      <required>DNS TTL handling and runtime sync safety scenarios covered.</required>
      <required>No silent rule leakage between dynamic domain bindings and static CIDR sets.</required>
    </Phase-2-Gate>
    <Phase-3-Gate>
      <required>Admin observability endpoints and UI surfaces reviewed for auth and data correctness.</required>
    </Phase-3-Gate>
    <Phase-4-Gate>
      <required>Production rollout review includes rollback, host-tool compatibility and secrets-safe deploy impact.</required>
    </Phase-4-Gate>
    <Phase-5-Gate>
      <required>Operator-issued configs are generated through backend provisioning and connect with the same topology semantics as web-issued configs.</required>
      <required>Repeated manual issuance does not create silent duplicate active clients.</required>
      <required>Complimentary internal access stays explicit in state and does not invoke payment-provider logic.</required>
      <required>Backend-driven peer changes become active on live awg0 without manual operator sync steps.</required>
    </Phase-5-Gate>
    <Phase-6-Gate>
      <required>Legacy single-client users are migrated to deterministic primary devices without losing active access.</required>
      <required>Plan device limits are persisted and enforced before any new peer provisioning.</required>
    </Phase-6-Gate>
    <Phase-7-Gate>
      <required>User device creation, revoke and rotate flows pass deterministic module-level checks and preserve one peer per logical device.</required>
      <required>Revoking a device frees a slot; rotating a config does not silently create a second active device.</required>
    </Phase-7-Gate>
    <Phase-8-Gate>
      <required>Suspicious handshake reuse leaves structured evidence, admin can review and enforce on a specific device peer, and automatic blocking remains either explicitly disabled or supported by bounded false-positive evidence.</required>
      <required>Blocked devices do not quietly regain access through stale peers or freed slots.</required>
    </Phase-8-Gate>
  </phase-gates>

  <agent-reporting>
    <rule>Always list which commands were actually executed and which were only planned.</rule>
    <rule>When tests are still planned but not implemented, say that explicitly instead of implying coverage exists.</rule>
    <rule>Every routing-critical report must name the decision reason branch that was affected.</rule>
  </agent-reporting>

  <failure-triage-packet>
    <field>contract_or_scenario</field>
    <field>expected_evidence</field>
    <field>observed_evidence</field>
    <field>first_divergent_module</field>
    <field>first_divergent_marker</field>
    <field>suggested_next_action</field>
  </failure-triage-packet>
</verification-plan>
